Prot.
I want to explain to
you.
the things that I want
to learn in Emacs
this coming weeks,
we have a session on
Saturday,
actually.
so I
haven't opened Emacs in two
weeks.
I don't know, a week,
two weeks. I don't know.
And why? Because there's a
lot of friction.
Okay. I want to talk
to Prot. I want to
explain Prot. Okay. Hold on.
Let me switch here.
Prot.
I want to explain to
you.
This is stupid. Okay. No,
let's be serious here.
So I want to
explain Prot. I want to
record a video.
On the things that I
want to learn in Emacs
this coming weeks,
we have a session on
Saturday,
actually. OK,
so I
haven't opened Emacs in two
weeks.
I don't know, a week,
two weeks. I don't know.
And why? Because there's a
lot of friction. OK.
It is not because of
evil mode, okay? So don't
think that, okay, so
you should use evil mode
on Emacs because that is
going to remove the friction
and you're already used to
your
modal editing.
No, that's not what I'm
talking about. I'm talking about
the workflow, like it is
too different.
I don't care about control
P, control N,
and that's all I know
in Emacs. And control L.
I don't care about those.
You know, I'll use them.
Okay. Or the arrows, whatever.
Okay. Or control X, control
S, like
control X, control C. I
don't know what that does.
Or, you know, like a
thousand. Sistering.
Not opening Emacs in two
weeks
is dishonoring your family.
oh man
but
that is what i'm trying
to fix
because i'm learning new things
but i
haven't learned how to adapt
emacs to my workflow
so
that i keep
using it in the future
okay
if i
find a way to bridge
that gap
i will
Use it more and more.
Okay,
so
First thing for
first things first. Okay,
the way that I navigate
sessions
in
My terminal, okay
Right here
in this section. I'm going
to paste a clip.
I hope that my editor
Editor
pay attention motherfucker. Okay
here
You have to delete what
I'm saying right now, bitch,
okay? Because this is not
going to make sense. Or
should we leave it in?
It makes it more exciting
if we leave it in,
right? But okay,
pay attention.
Here
is where you have to
put
the session section that I
talked about
a moment ago, okay?
Here.
Put that now.
Now.
Add it,
okay?
so it didn't work
this way back then
but then he reached out
and said hey christian
you talked about sessions
i implemented sessions in kitty
okay so
that is why i ditched
tmux pretty much okay so
that's what you see me
doing all the time
Let me try to explain
sessions briefly for like the
10th or 20th time. Okay.
So
this is just a way
for me to navigate to
different projects. Okay.
And this is going to
be useful for Prot as
well.
I think,
but it's going to be
mixed all together, but
I'm in my daily note
session here. Okay. I have
this other session. I have
my home session.
I want to go to
my dot files.
It's not open right now.
Okay. But
with the key press, I
can go to my dot
files.
But
it automatically opens new of
them here
because I configured it that
way. Okay. So this is
new of them
in
this session.
The name of the session
is called here dot files.
Here is the path
to this. Okay.
If I open a new
tab on this session,
that is not going to
open new of them,
but I'm in that path.
Okay.
The nice thing about this
is that each session for
me is pretty much.
usually a
github project okay so i'm
just going to restore the
session right here i
have
three new
event buffers open
and this is a github
repo okay so
all of the changes that
i perform on this
github.files latest
are
in kit
okay
so
all of it is here
i just push my changes
if i switch to another
session my blog post for
example
here you can see the
path
this is an nfs mounted
volume on mac os okay
but
same thing
it's just a session
and
if i open a new
tab
you know
here is the path
i can open open code
and tell it to do
something
on this specific
github repo okay so
if i open here
um
lazy git which
is
alt g i think yeah
here it is okay
so
I can just push the
changes to GitHub on this
repo. Okay. So
it's just,
does that make sense?
Does it make sense? No.
Yep.
I think it does make
sense. Let's put another example,
a useful example.
What else is useful for
people here? My keyboard. Okay.
That is
another useful one.
If I need to make
changes on my keyboard, I'm
like, okay,
so let's bring up this
Toucan
session.
Here is the path for
it. I just go to
it
and there's the session right
there.
I don't open any of
them here.
automatically, but I could if
I want it. Okay.
This is the name of
the session in KDE.
You can have multiple tabs
here if I want, you
know,
open code
in one of them so
it works on something.
My new of them,
I can have it open
here.
And if I push changes
to GitHub, this is a
GitHub repo pretty much.
Okay. So
if I make changes to
my file,
let's restore this.
And let's say that I
change this to,
I don't know,
this right
if i push the changes
you know
on this repo
i have everything self contained
a
session for me personally
is a github repo
okay
not all the time okay
i can discard changes quite
easily here
just discard it
that's it
i'm back
the original state okay so
That is one of the
things that I want to
touch on with Prot. Just
show him
how I navigate
sessions
in my terminal right now.
And each one of them
is a repo,
usually GitHub repo
that has it's
like
changes that I push to
GitHub, each one is independent,
okay? So
the list of sessions that
I have open right now,
you know,
take a look at the
path of each one of
them.
They're in my GitHub directory.
This repo,
this repo right here. So
I can
quickly
switch between
sessions
and I'm,
you know, I keep working
on what I had on
that session, okay? So...
Okay,
so now, Prat,
that you know how sessions
work,
okay?
I would like to do
something similar in Emacs.
Why?
Because I'm just used to
that workflow, you know?
I like switching to our
repo really fast.
Do what I have to
do.
Commit my changes. I know
Mac is the tool on
Emacs. It's fine. I'm going
to get used to it.
Switch to another repo.
Work on what I have
to do on that other
repo or project.
Commit the changes to GitHub.
Okay.
And push them.
Switch to another repo.
Do the work that I
need to do on that
other
self-contained
independent repo.
commit it, push it,
and like that, you know?
I switch around between different
repos throughout the whole day.
My .files,
my work-related stuff.
Like,
I spend a lot of
time in my work. My
notes sometimes, okay?
You know, my blog posts
sometimes. But...
That is the way that
I work. And I need
to find
an easier way to work
that way in Emacs. Okay.
I can use their ad.
I don't give a crap
about
the tools that I use,
but I need to
find something. Okay. Let me
show you as well
how I open files when
I navigate to a session.
Okay. This is my daily
note right now.
But if I go to
my files,
let's say that I need
to look for something.
Okay.
I want to get to
it.
the snap of a finger
like this listen
fast brother so
what i do is type
f f
i don't care if the
key bind is different
i don't care
if the tool looks different
i'll get used to it
if i have to use
the
default emacs tool it's fine
just give me something
that allows me to search
for files
in that project okay
i don't want to search
the files across my entire
system because that doesn't make
sense i just want to
search for the files
in
the project or the workspace
or whatever it's called i'm
on okay so
all of the files that
i can search here
are the files in my
dot files
that's it
okay i
don't want to see files
in my root directory i
in my downloads here
chose the files
and that specific
session all
all right if that makes
sense
okay so if i want
to open
what
my init.el
file
is right there okay
Then I'm like, you know
what? I need to make
changes to my
kitty
file. My kitty config file.
FF.
I don't care about the
key map. So I just
type here kitty.
Boom. I'm right there. Okay.
FF.
Now let's say that I
want to make changes to
my, this
suck site session file. Boom.
I'm right there. Okay.
Can I see my list
of open buffers? Yes, I
can. They're right here.
I can close them from
here.
I don't care about that.
It doesn't have to be
a plugin.
I just need to find
a quick way
to open files in Emacs.
Because if I type control
X, control F,
and fucking type the entire
path to the file, brother,
you already lost me, okay?
I'm like, mm-mm, that's too
much friction. So I just...
That's one of the things
that I need to work
on first, okay?
That is what creates most
of the friction.
I don't know how to
navigate.
I don't know if sessions
are a thing in Emacs.
don't know if there are
workspaces. I don't know what
they are. I don't know
how to use
file picker.
that allows me to search
for files. I want to
type the name of the
file,
I want it to find
it for me,
and I want it to
open it for me
in that session,
okay?
And I want to have
my list of
buffers open
in that session only, okay?
Here's the buffers that I
have open in this session.
If I switch to my
blog post session,
which is the one right
here,
let's open, let's restore the
session, okay?
Which files are open in
this session?
Just this one, YouTube memberships.
Okay, that's it.
No other files are open
here.
If I do FF here
to search for a file,
I will
be able to look for
files
only
in this
session.
I don't care about the
files in my .files.
I don't want them mixed
together here.
I just want the files.
Does that make sense?
Does it make sense? I
think it makes sense, right?
So
if I want to open
this one,
I can open it. It's
fine.
Which buffers do I have
open in this session?
Just these two buffers, okay?
That's all I want.
I don't want a
list
of 100
buffers
with all the buffers that
I have open in my
entire... No,
that's too much, okay? I
just want to keep things
segmented,
isolated,
independent.
Does that make sense?
I think it does. Okay.
So
that's the first thing.
The other thing. Okay.
Okay.
is that
i capture my
thoughts
pretty quickly
in Neovim
and that's what i have
here
daily note driven workflow
i don't need it to
keep
be the same in emacs
it doesn't matter okay
um but i'm what i'm
trying to say with this
is okay
let's say that i'm in
my dot files okay
then
i usually remember oh you
know what
on saturday i need to
ask Prot
um
this thing okay
okay so i just come
here
to my daily notes
and i just add a
to do here
right uh
ask Prot about
uh sessions
in emacs
i just added there
i move on with my
life i don't care where
i put this i just
need a place to put
it
so
i use this daily note
a lot
it's just like a
scratch pad we could say
the information here is not
like
super relevant
you know
but it
can help me if i
want to create
other files in the future
if that makes sense okay
I can compile
information that I leave on
each day scratch pad
and create useful files in
the future okay
so
What is the way to
capture that
in
some sort of this
daily notes
driven workflow?
I want to get there
fast. Okay. Let's say that
I'm on a different date.
Let's say that I'm
here. Okay.
This is Monday. This was
Monday.
What did I leave here?
You see,
most of the time doesn't
make sense.
Okay.
It's just stuff that I
copy here,
paste into an AI, you
know?
And some of the stuff
does make sense, okay? But
I want to get to
this quite fast. Take a
look at where I'm at
right now. I'm on Monday.
Let's say that I'm in
my .files, right? And I
remember, oh, you know what?
I need to do something.
I'm just going to press
a single key.
It's going to take me
right there.
Do I want to add
a to-do here on this
note?
I don't care. But if
I want to add it
on today's...
Daily notes, I can do
it as well. I have
another key map. GT
takes me
to today's day.
Okay. July 30th. Okay.
And go back to the
previous day
where I was before. I
can just jump. It doesn't
matter. I can do that
in Emacs for sure. But
what I'm talking about is
friction.
I don't want to create
a file,
put all the
front matter.
Because I will forget what
I needed to capture
by the time I'm done
creating the file. This is
automatic,
right?
I switch to the daily
note if it doesn't exist,
create it,
and I just start typing.
And that's it.
If I need to organize
the information later,
I do it. If I
need to process it. Let
me give you an example
here. I'm just going to
look for my files.
Let's search for
Debian, okay?
Let's search for Debian.
Brother, but this Debian is
just an open, like an
empty file.
Is it? Is it? Is
it?
There's three references to this
file.
GR.
Oh, we can see the
references.
What are these references?
On July 18th,
I referenced this file.
The same day, three times.
Let's take a look at
it.
I open it
and I'm like,
oh, okay. So this is
where I did. Okay.
That's where I have this
link right here.
And that is something that
I want to learn as
well, how to do an
Emacs.
How do I link notes
together? Okay.
If I type GD here,
it's going to take me
to this Debian note
that I have there,
right?
Control always gonna take me
back.
If I type GD
on this other link,
it's going to take me
to this XOA node,
GD,
right?
And you may think,
but
this is an empty node
as well, is it?
GR is gonna show me.
On the 18th on Saturday,
I referenced this node three
times, okay?
And I can see the
preview here on the right
hand side, okay?
I can,
you know, just
see what this is about.
But you're using your mouse.
Why are you such a
little brother?
Like, grow up, okay? Sometimes
using the mouse is just
faster.
What
was the
shortcut to
scroll down the preview on
the right?
I don't remember. Okay.
I remember.
What is it?
I don't care. Okay.
But
you see what I'm talking
about? You see what I'm
talking about? So
I just need to find
a way
to link nodes
like this.
Let's start with the basics.
Okay.
What would be...
useful way
to do this
to go to my
daily note
start capturing
where I need to capture
and from here
link to other notes
okay
the way that I do
it here
if I'm able to do
that with org
or if I know how
to do that with org
I'm going to start opening
my daily notes
in org,
linking notes there
and doing all this stuff
there. So
otherwise I'm not going to
open Emacs and just go
through the, no,
it's,
I need to start using
it seriously
so that I can give
it a fair chance. Okay.
Those are the things that
I think
I'm interested in. What else?
Linking files, we already talked
about this. Yep, we talked
about everything pretty much,
right?
We talked about this. Sessions,
I talked about that.
I talked about this. I
talked about this as well.
I talked about everything,
okay?
And that's pretty much it,
I think. But
those are the questions that
I have
and the stuff that I
like to cover,
not on Saturday, but in
the following weeks, because I
know
that
I didn't give you enough
time to
understand what's going on and
all that. But in the
following weeks,
if we can cover this
would be
amazing.